ATHM Textile Industry Stereographs 6524/006 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II: General Images Organized by Textile Related Subject
  - Warping and Dressing (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Item 9: Warping room in the great Olympian Cotton Mills, Columbia, South Carolina (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts female textile workers warping cotton. The cotton thread is unwound from the small spools in the creel (to the right), run through several bars in order get the proper tension, and ultimately rewound on to the big spool at the bottom of the machine, the warp beam. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900- 1910. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 10: Drawing the warp, front view, Dallas Cotton Mills, Dallas, Texas, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-whtie image depicts a female textile worker drawing cotton warp. This warping process is drawing the cotton thread into a ball, rather than a beam. Ball warping is a system of gathering together a large number of threads into a long, loose rope that is made up into a ball. Ball warping is usually done for convenience in dyeing, shipping, etc., after which the yarn is run onto a beam. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 11: Warpers, Langley Cotton Mill, Langley, S.C., 1890 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black- and-white image depicts female textile workers standing beside warping machines. Warping prepares the warp for weaving. The creels (behind the warping machines) feed the threads into the machine, and then onto the warp beam (in front of the machines). No. 10 in a series of images of the Langley Cotton Mill, which was formally known as the Langley Manufacturing Co. Photographed by J. A. Palmer, Aiken, S.C. Augusta, Ga.: E. H. Pughe, printer. 18 x 9 cm. See also Item 29, in this folder.
    - Item 12: The spindle of the twentieth century, Fall River, Mass., 1903 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts cotton warping machinery. The warper pulls the threads from the creels on the left and winds it onto the beam just visible on the right. Mill location in Fall River is not specified. Littleton, New Hampshire: B. W. Kilburn. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 13: Warping machines, Massachusetts Cotton Mills, Lowell, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts warping machines. Handwritten on back of Copy A: [The Massacusetts Cotton mill, Lowell, Mass]. New York: H. Ropes & Co., ca. 1864-1883. 18 x 9 cm. Copy B.
    - Item 14: Warping machines in a cotton mill, Augusta, Ga., 1901 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts cotton warping machines and spinning machines. The image is identifical to Item 8, in this folder, but on the reverse of this card is a Greek translation of the caption handwritten in ink, and a stamp of the name "Z. Oikonomou" and the words "en Peiraiei." It seems that at one point the card was available in the Greek market, distributed (?) by Z. Oikonomou in Peraios. North Bennington, Vt.: H. C. White Co. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 15: The Great Spooling Room, Stine Mill, Fall River, Mass., 1903 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and published by B. W. Kilburn. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image actually shows warpers in action, not spooling. 17.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 16: Warping room, cotton mill, Lowell, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts cotton warping machines. Warping is the process of preparing a warp for weaving; the warper pulls the threads from the creels on the left and winds them onto the warp beam on the right. The specific mill in Lowell is not identified, but this is no. 34 of a Lowell, Mass., series published by Marston & Prince. Lowell, Mass.: Marston & Prince, ca. 1871-1886. 18 x 10 cm.
    - Item 17: Warping Room, Brainerd & Armstrong, New London, Conn. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      ca. 1880s. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image shows what appears to be a very crowded warping room at Brainerd & Armstrong, which manufactured silk thread. 17.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 18: Warping machines, Naumkeag Cotton factory, Salem, Mass (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts cotton warping machines in the Naumkeag Steam Cotton Co. mill. The warpers pull threads from the creels on the left and wind them onto a beam, which is the large circular beam on the lower right of each warper. ca. 1900. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 19: No. 616, Spooling Room [Warping], Mechanics Mill, Fall River, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Littleton, New Hampshire: Photographed and publsihed by Kilburn Bros., ca.1875-1885. Black and white image shows rows of warping machines in the Mechanics Mill in Fall River. 17 x 8.25 cm.
    - Item 20: Warping Room, Stevens & Co.'s Woolen Mills (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Haverhill, Mass.: Anderson, ca. 1890. Gelatin silver print. Black and white image shows the warping room in the Stevens & Co. mill in Haverhill, Mass. (formerly known as the Haverhill Flannel Factory). A warper is in the foreground, behind which stands a male employee in a jacket and hat; he has a mustache. 17.75 x 10 cm.
    - Item 21: Spooling Room, Lawrence Mill, Lowell, Mass., 1891 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Photographed and published by B. W. Kilburn, Littleton, New Hampshire Albumen print. Black and white image actually shows the warping process in the Lawrence Manufacturing Co. in Lowell, Mass. Warping is the process of preparing a warp for weaving or knitting and occurs after the spooling process (winding yarn onto a spool). 17.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 22: Amoskeag Mills, Gingham Mill, Warping Room, Manchester, New Hampshire (Box 10, Folder 2)
      #53 of Manchester views, published by C. K. Burns, 1018 Elm Street, Manchester, New Hampshire, ca. 1880s. Black and white image depicts the warping room in the gingham mill. Threads are being wound onto the beam warper in the foreground, in which the different colors for the gingham can already be seen. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 23: No. 1 Mill Dressing [Warping] Room, Cocheco Manufacturing Co., Dover, New Hampshire (Box 10, Folder 2)
      ca. 1880s. Black and white image shows row of warping machines, where the warp is being wound onto a beam. 17.75 x 10 cm.
    - Item 24: Warping machine at work in a big, up-to-date woolen mill (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts male textile workers warping woolen threads. The warping machine is winding off threads from several spools at once and laying the strands closely, side by side, around one long warp beam in front of the worker. Location of mill not given. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 26: Sectional warping, Castle Hedingham, England (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a woman operating a warping machine. The threads are drawn from the bobbins into a section, which is wound around the reel. Sectional warping is a system of warping, often called the silk systerm, in which the warp is built up in sections by winding it on a large reel. After the required length has been run off for the first section the reel is moved a short distance and the second section is built up beside the first. After obtaining the necessary number of sections in this way all are run off simultaneously on a beam. Castle Hedingham is located near Halstead, Essex, England. ca. 1970s. 15.25 x 10 cm.
    - Item 26: Hornby's Mill, Blackburn [England] (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts two male textile workers in the background, standing behind two rows of warping machines in a warping room. Warping is the process of preparing a warp for weaving. The warping machines pull threads from the creels (behind the machines) and wind them onto the large beam in front of the machines. Several loose warp beams on the floor in the center of the room. The handwritten message on the reverse calls this a "winding room," but the more accurate term would be a warping room. Printed in Great Britain. ca. 1902-1915. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 27: Slashers, Cotton (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts cotton slashers inside a mill, possibly in Lawrence, Mass. Slashing is the operation of sizing a warp on a slasher. The objects are to give each warp thread a coating of size mixture, to dry the threads, and to run the desired number of threads on a loom beam. ca. 1900. 18 x 10 cm.
    - Item 28: Warping machine, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a cotton warping machine. Warping is the process of preparing a warp for weaving. The warper pulls the threads from the creels behind it and winds them onto the warp beam in the front of the machine. Written on the reverse: [No. 9 Warper]. A. B. Hamor, Lawrence Views, ca. 1880. 17.75 x 10 cm.
    - Item 29: Warpers, Langley Cotton Mill, Langley, S.C. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts warping machines in the Langley Cotton Mill in Langley, S.C. Warping is the process of preparing a warp for weaving. The warper pulls the threads from the creels (behind the machine) and winds it onto a warp beam (in front of the machine). A warp beam lies partially on the floor in the foreground. No. 9 in a series of images of the Langley Cotton Mill, which was formally known as the Langley Manufacturing Co. Photographed by J. A. Palmer, Aiken, S.C. Augusta, Ga.: E. H. Pughe, printer, ca. 1890. 17.75 x 10 cm. See also Item 11, in this folder.
    - Item 30: Drawing in Warp, Rear View, Dallas Cotton Mills, Dallas, Texas, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and -white image deipcts a female textile worker drawing in warp. Drawing in is the operation of entering the warp ends from the warp beam through the eyes of the correct heddles on the respective harnesses. This view shows the threads being drawn from the creels into the warper. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 31: Warping, silk industry, South Manchester, Conn., 1914 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts female textile workers preparing a silk warp for weaving by unwinding the silk threads from spools on creels (on the left); the threads are then wound onto a reel (on the right). These reels are called Ferris Wheels. Cheney Bros. was the only silk mill in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 32: Beaming, Winding Warp from Large Reel on to Loom Beam--Silk Industry, South Manchester, Conn., 1914 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a female textile worker beaming off silk. She is operating a machine that winds warp from a large reel (the Ferris Wheel seen in Item 31, in this folder) on to the loom beam. The operative is watching for threads that may have dropped or crossed. Cheney Bros. was the only silk mill in South Manchester, Conn. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 33: Drawing warp for weaving silk cloth in extensive silk mills at Paterson, N.J. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts male textile workers drawing the warp. On the left of the view you see the hundreds of spools of silk. From these the men draw threads, one at a time, through reeds that look like fine combs, on top of the spool frame. The threads are then wound on the large reels, seen at the right of the view. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 34: Warping Room, Worsteds, Washington Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Albumen print, ca. 1880. No. 17 in the series, Interior Views of the Washington Mills. Published by A. B. Hamor. Image shows warping machinery on the left and center. 17.5 x 10 cm.
    - Item 35: Preparing the warp for the looms - Brainerd & Armstrong's weaving department (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Color image shows women standing in a room with sloping ceilings that have pendant light fixtures and open beams. The women on the left are all facing away from the viewer and the women on the right are facing towards the viewer. Each stands next to a warp beam on which the silk thread is being wound for the looms. Brainerd & Armstrong was located in New London, Conn. Chilton Printing Co., Philadelphia, Pa. ca. 1907-1915. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 36: Sectional warping (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a male textile worker standing by a reel used in sectional warping. Sectional warping is a system of warping, often called the silk systerm, in which the warp is built up in sections by winding it on a large reel. After the required length has been run off for the first section the reel is moved a short distance and the second section is built up beside the first. After obtaining the necessary number of sections in this way all are run off simultaneously on a beam. Here you can see the large hooks on the large reel separating the sections, which will be simultaneously wound onto the small beam in front. ca. 1918-1930. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 37: Slashing or starching the warp, Dallas Cotton Mills, Dallas, Texas, 1905 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a male textile worker operating a slasher. The work of the slasher is to pass the yarn, or warp as it is now called, through a starch box, dry it, and rewind it onto a loom beam (seen here in the foreground). Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 38: Slashing machine which sizes the warp-yarn in a modern woolen mill (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a slashing machine (slasher). Slashing is the operation of sizing a warp on a slasher. The objects are to give each warp thread a coating of size mixture, to dry the threads, and to run the desired number of threads on a loom beam. Stamped on reverse: "San Bernardino Country Free Library" but the location of this image is unknown. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 39: A mechanical twister at work--silk industry, South Machester, Conn., 1914 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a female textile worker operating a mechanical twister. The machine is run by power and duplicates the motion of the human twister's thumb and fingers by running the threads together between two rubber pads. It then cuts off the loose ends with a knife. This photo was most likely taken in the Cheney Bros. plant in South Manchester. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 40: Warp tying machine, Model E, Barber-Colman Company (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a warp tying machine used in the process of tying-in, during which the machine unites the threads of a new warp and the ends remaining from a former warp, in order to avoid hand drawing-in. The machine selects an end of the old warp and knots it to the corresponding end in the new warp, then trims the knot. The Barber-Colman Company was based in Rockford, Ill. ca. This image is identical to those of Items 41 and 42, in this folder. ca. 1910-1918. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 41: Warp tying machine, Model E, Barber-Colman Company (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a warp tying machine used in the process of tying-in, during which the machine unites the threads of a new warp and the ends remaining from a former warp, in order to avoid hand drawing-in. The machine selects an end of the old warp and knots it to the corresponding end in the new warp, then trims the knot. The Barber-Colman Company was based in Rockford, Ill. This image is identical to those of Items 40 and 42, in this folder. ca. 1910-1918. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 42: Warp tying machine, Model E, Barber-Colman Company (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Warp tying machine, Model E, Barber-Colman Company. Black-and-white image depicts a warp tying machine used in the process of tying-in, during which the machine unites the threads of a new warp and the ends remaining from a former warp, in order to avoid hand drawing-in. The machine selects an end of the old warp and knots it to the corresponding end in the new warp, then trims the knot. The Barber-Colman Company was based in Rockford, Ill. This image is identical to those of Items 40 and 41, in this folder, although the machine label is in a different place. ca. 1910-1918. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 43: Warp tying machine, Model K, Barber-Colman Company (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Black-and-white image depicts a warp tying machine used in the process of tying-in, during which the machine unites the threads of a new warp and the ends remaining from a former warp, in order to avoid hand drawing-in. The machine selects an end of the old warp and knots it to the corresponding end in the new warp, then trims the knot. The Barber-Colman Company was based in Rockford, Ill. ca. 1910-1918. 8.75 x 13.75 cm.
    - Item 44: Warp drawing-in, Pacific Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Gelatin silver print. Black and white image of an interior room in the Pacific Mills in Lawrence, Mass., showing the drawing-in process. Drawing-in is the operation of entering the warp ends from the warp beam through the eyes of the correct heddles on the respective harnesses, which is what the woman seated in the foreground is doing. Both male and female laborers are visible. ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 8.5 cm. Copy A.
    - Item 45: Warp drawing-in, Pacific Mills, Lawrence, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Gelatin silver print. Black and white image of an interior room in the Pacific Mills in Lawrence, Mass., showing the drawing-in process. Drawing-in is the operation of entering the warp ends from the warp beam through the eyes of the correct heddles on the respective harnesses, which is what the woman seated in the foreground is doing. Both male and female laborers are visible. ca. 1900-1920. 17.5 x 8.5 cm. Copy B.
    - Item 46: Typical Warper Room, Fall River Cotton Mills [Fall River, Mass.], 1909 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Color image of rows of warpers and warp beams in an unidentified cotton mill. A beam warper is a machine placed in front of a V-shaped creel which contains the packages of yarn. The warper winds numerous threads in parallel order onto a beam. Published by F.P. Charlton Co., Fall River, Mass. Made in Germany. Postmarked Nov. 5, 1909 in Fall River. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 47: Slasher Room of a Fall River Cotton Mill [Fall River, Mass.] (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Color image of male employees posing next to slasher equipment in an unidentified mill. Slashing is the operation of sizing a warp on a slasher. The object is to give each warp thread a coating of size mixture, to dry the threads, and to run the desired number of threads on a loom beam (seen in the front of each slasher). Published by F.P. Charlton Co., Fall River, Mass. Made in Germany. ca. 1907-1909. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 48: Modern spinner girl 1930s (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Photograph by Lewis W. Hine, 1874-1940. Photo-study for the National Research Project of the Works Progress Administration. Brooklyn, N.Y.: The Brooklyn Museum, ca. 1977. Black and white image shows woman standing in front of a cotton warper creel tender (Barber-Colman cheeses). 14.25 x 10.5 cm.
    - Item 49: Warping-woof and creel (Box 10, Folder 2)
      Tolson Memorial Museum, Huddersfield, England. [no later than 1962] Black and white image shows warping-woof and creel (warping frame). 14 x 9 cm.
  - Weaving (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Item 1: Telaio a mano [hand loom] (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Museo didattico della Seta Como. Foto Enzo Pifferi stampa Tip Ed. Cesare Nani.
    - Item 2: Weaving woolen blankets on a primitive hand loom, Telemarken, Norway, 1906 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts a woman working at a loom. Down below is a roll of cloth already woven. Most Norwegian families raise their own sheep and spin their own wool. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company. 18 x 9 cm.
    - Item 3: Tape weaving, Nantucket, Mass., 1908 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts Phebe Pinkham Folger weaving tape in her home; tape is a narrow strip of stout cotton, linen, or other textile material used as a flat string for tying purposes, for binding, etc. Caption: "Tape Weaving. The strands of time woven with the threads of life. A tape binding Nantucket's past and present. Capt. John Pitman, age 93, and Phebe Pinkham Folger, age 92, for 68 years his beloved wife." Published by M. W. Boyer, Nantucket, Mass. Made in Germany. Photo only copyright T. Coffin Pitman, Nantucket, Mass. 9 x 13.75 cm.
    - Item 4: Typical French Canadian Homestead, Province of Quebec, Canada (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Color image depicts two women working at a loom. A baby sleeps in a cradle on the right with another small child looking over the cradle. Caption on reverse: "In the typical French-Canadian home built of handhewn timbers and furnished with hand-made furniture, the spinning wheel and loom are still used. Grandmother and Mother are weaving the famous Murray Bay Homespun an industry-sponsored by the Canada Steamship Lines." Novelty Mfg. & Art Co. Ltd., Montreal. ca. 1920-1930. 9 x 13.75 cm.
    - Item 5: Oldest Pi Beta Phi weaver, Gatlinburg, Tenn. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts an elderly woman working at a loom. A younger woman stands in the rear. Weaving was first taught at the Pi Beta Phi settlement school in Gatlinburg in 1925. Handwritten note on the back of the postcard but it was not stamped or mailed. Jack Huff Photo, ca. 1939. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 6: James Alexander Weaving Shop, Monroe, N.Y. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Old Museum Village of Smith's Clove, Monroe, Orange County, N.Y. Color image depicts a woman working at a spinning wheel in front of a hand loom. Pub. by Walter H. Miller & Co., Inc., Williamsburg, Va. [after 1950] 13.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 7: Habitant spinning and weaving making, Matane, Province of Quebec, 1934 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts two women, one working a spinning a wheel, the other, a loom. Made in Canada. Date based on calendar on back wall: August 1934. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 8: Cornelius O'Sullivan, Handwoven Homespuns, Raleigh Bonane, Kenmare [Ireland] (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and- white image depicts Cornelius O'Sullivan sitting at a loom. Handwritten on reverse some notes, measurements, and prices. ca. 1950. 14 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 9: Weaving, Pi Beta Phi school, Gatlinburg, Tenn. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts a woman working at a loom, with a spinning wheel in the background. Weaving was first taught at the Pi Beta Phi settlement school in Gatlinburg in 1925. [1939?]. 13.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 10: Loom room, Llewsac Lodge, Bedford, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Black-and-white image depicts two women working at looms. Another loom is at the right. Llewsac Lodge was the Bedford branch of the Frances E. Willard settlement in Boston. It served both as a home for needy older women as well as a vacation spot for younger working women from the settlement in Boston. Weaving was one way guests could help pay for their stay at the Lodge. The undivided back postcard suggests a date no later than 1907, but the Bedford property was not purchased until 1909. ca. 1910-1915. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 11: The loom room in the country store attic, Wiggins Old Tavern at Hotel Northampton, Northampton, Mass. (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Tinted image depicts a woman working at a loom on the right. Several spinning wheels and a great wheel can be seen on the left. The Hotel Northampton was constructed in 1927. ca. 1930s. 13.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 12: Top: Miniature silk loom / Bottom: Habitant loom, Province of Quebec, Canada (Box 10, Folder 3)
      Color image depicts (top) a young girl holding a kitten, sitting by a miniature loom, and (bottom) four women working at looms. "Canadian Art Deeptone" Series. Made in Canda. ca. 1930s. 8.75 x 14 cm.